We pick up today's דף Daf today's ס"ז. Samech Zayin. We pick
up at the top of ס"ז, Samech Zayin, first line, and we
are wrapping up a discussion in דף Daf of the different types
of liquids and cleansers used to in order to remove the stains
and as a way of actually number one getting into a point
where it no longer has this considered a stain, the גמרא Gemorah
discussed even if you knew definitely it was blood, and number two
that if it didn't remove it you would be able to determine
it wasn't a stain. So we're going through the various cleansers. Let's
take a look now top of ס"ז עמוד א'. Samech Zayin Amud
Aleph. איזו רוק תפל, Eizo Rok Tafal,
one of them is this what do you call it this tasteless
spit. So what is this tasteless spit? תנא, Tana, כל שלא טעם
כלום מהערב. kol shelo taam klum mehaerev. So the ברייתא Beraisa says
somebody who has not tasted anything from the night, from the night
before, but there's still a little ambiguity so let's see what the
גמרא Gemorah says about this. רב פפא קמיה דרבא Rav Pappa kemei
d'Rava was learning this in front of רבא, Rava, he understood that
what it meant was כמאן דאמר לא טעים מדיבאורסא, keman damar lo
taim midibaorsa, like somebody who would say, you know, I didn't eat
anything the night before.
So אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava, so רבא Rava said to
him, no, רבא Rava said I don't agree with that פשט. Pshat.
מי קתני בערב, mi kateni baerev,
it didn't say somebody who didn't eat anything at night, which could
mean you haven't eaten anything from the entire night before, מהערב קתני,
mehaerev kateni,
from since it's been night, לאפוקי היכא דקדמו ואכיל le'afokei heicha d'kadmu
v'achil
to exclude a case where you ate first where you ate like
in the morning, where you got up you know you got up
basically where you got up early and you ate a little bit
before it
became the type of two people doing צדקה Tzedakah doing חסד Chesed
here.
Okay, so it basically he says it doesn't mean you didn't have
dinner last night like when the doctor tells you right you have
to have these you know you have to have a test I
don't want you know you shouldn't eat anything right you're allowed to
have dinner right it's since midnight. Right you're not supposed to eat
anything from the time you go to sleep till you take the
test. So that's basically what רבא Rava is saying, meaning he didn't
get up early before morning and have something to eat but he
could have had dinner last night.
Okay, so let's see the גמרא's Gemorah going to try to make
this a little more specific. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי
יוחנן, Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, איזו רוק תפל,
Eizo Rok Tafal, so what is this tasteless spit? כל שעבר עליו
חצות לילה בשינה. kol sheavar alav chatzos layla bsheina.
So actually they you know as opposed to us we could stay
up till midnight and then go to bed but if you don't
have electric lights you go to bed you know when it gets
dark. So he says really what it means is is that you've
been you slept and now it's midnight and now any spit that
you'll have now falls into that category. Okay, so you don't have
to sleep the whole night, you slept and it's midnight and presumably
you haven't eaten anything since the time that you wake up, no
since the time
that you went to sleep. You still could have had dinner though.
Right, you did. So basically you don't eat since you wake up
and he says that basically it's you've gone through midnight
but you had to actually have
so the גמרא's Gemorah going to say למימרא דשינה תליא מילתא, lemeimra
dsheina talyia milsa, does that suggest that it requires having gone to
sleep? והתנן vehasnan we learned in the משנה, Mishnah, ישן כל היום
אין זה רוק תפל, yashen kol hayom ein zeh rok tafal, it's
actually a ברייתא, Beraisa, תניא, Tanya, that if you slept the whole
day it is not considered רוק תפל, rok tafal, it has to
be nighttime. נעור כל הלילה הרי זה רוק תפל, neor kol halayla
harei zeh rok tafal, if you're awake the whole night it also
doesn't count. So I was thinking about this נעור כל הלילה neor
kol halayla oh I'm sorry הרי זה, harei zeh, excuse me, it
does count. הרי זה רוק תפל, harei zeh rok tafal, so you
see you don't have to be asleep. So the גמרא Gemorah says
התם במיסנמנם, hasam b'misnamnem, there when it says awake the whole night
it doesn't literally mean awake the whole night it means dozing off.
It doesn't mean so היכי דמי מסנמנם, heichi dami misnamnem, what does
this mean because this is a phrase used a couple of times
in the גמרא Gemorah in the
משנה. Mishnah. Exactly this is repeated look at this repeated like five
times in ש"ס, Shas, this little phrase this little description of what
dozing off means. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, נים ולא נים
תיר ולא תיר, num vlo num teir vlo teir, you're asleep but
you're not really asleep, you're awake but you're not so awake. דקרו
ליה ועני dkaru lei vaanei they call you and you'll answer, huh,
yeah, what?
ולא ידע לאהדורי סברא, vlo yada lahadurei sevara, but you can't talk
sense, you can't talk reason, right, if somebody tells you to explain
something you wouldn't be able to explain it. ואי
מדכרו ליה
ve'ei
madkaru
lei but if they remind you, like, oh, is this what you
mean, is this whatever, מדכר, madkar, yeah, yeah, whatever. So you can
sort of like hear what somebody else is saying and respond to
it and even comprehend if it makes sense but you can't yourself
in a state articulate, you know, some some something of logic. So
pretty interesting description, anyway, so for some so that's what we say
is going on here. It doesn't literally mean fully awake, but you
have to be a little bit dozing and then that changes the
quality of the spit. Thinking about that like
isn't it like when you wake up like your mouth has this
whole morning taste to it, right, and it doesn't have that taste
if you're awake if you stay up at night. Does it have
that taste if you sleep during the day? It does. So it
must have to do with right,
I assume it's that your mouth is moving, it does something to
the spit which let it get stale when you're asleep. So probably
does have more to do with sleeping. The גמרא Gemorah combines it
both with sleeping and the nighttime.
Okay, תנא. Tana.
How much time
since the last time you
ate? So you think that there is a point. So then how
come again, how come the doctor says, well, I guess they are
trying to say not to eat the night before, and the amount
of time you go to sleep, it's the amount of time. Right,
it's like since midnight, because
those are important, right, you can't drink water, right?
That's not clear. Actually, it talks about eating, it doesn't talk about
drinking. Oh just eating, you're right. It says you didn't taste anything.
Yeah, you're right, you're right. All right, so anyway the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay. תנא: Tanna: השכים ושנה פרקו אין זה רוק
תפל. Hishkim v'shana pirko ein zeh rok tapel. So the same way
if you get up early and you eat, so you know, that's
now you've put food in your mouth and that changes the nature
of the spit, that's not good, even if you did it while
it was still midnight time. Also, if you get up early and
you literally it says you went over your chapter. So not exactly
clear, does it mean learning, does it mean yeah, so apparently you
have some regular thing that you learn in the morning or maybe
it's תורה, Torah, maybe it's even other things, but presumably anyway, if
you did some talking in the morning, that also gets it out
of that category,
which means it is no longer תפל. tapel. You mean you started
to דאווענען davnen then?
Maybe. Let's take a look.
עד כמה? Ad kama? How much? אמר רב יהודה בר שילא אמר
רב אסי אמר רבי אליעזר: Amar Rav Yehuda bar Shila amar Rav
Assi amar Rabbi Eliezer: כל שהוציא את רוב דיבורו של שלוש שעות.
Kol she'hotzi et rov diburo shel shalosh sha'ot. If you've done the
most of the talking that you'll do normally in the course of
three
hours. That's an interesting way of thinking in general about דף יומי
Daf Yomi
if you know two hours.
There you go. Well, I don't know, maybe the amount of talking
we do, at least I do during דף יומי Daf Yomi for
the next three hours of the day. But anyway, it's also an
interesting way of thinking about it like you know I mean sometimes
the בעלי מוסר Ba'alei Mussar talk about this like you know let's
say you imagine you had so many words to say during the
day. So then you have to use each word, like is this
a good use of this word if I only have so many
words to say during the day. So here the גמרא Gemara says
think about how many words you're going to say or how much
you're going to talk over the next three hours, have you spoken
that much, the majority of that, and once you have, it's no
longer רוק תפל. rok tapel.
I'm pretty quiet until I get to work. There you go.
There you go.
Okay. So anyway that is רוק תפל, rok tapel, something that you
you know
you
slept, it was night, and you haven't eaten anything since or spoken
too much since you woke up.
All this is cumulative.
All right. Apparently you need all those criteria. Okay. Now the גמרא
Gemara says מי גריסין Mei grisin what? What they have to talk
about that in the morning?
Well, I don't know, they have to this is what they thought
would help for a cleanser for the for the
stain. Were these doctors or men?
They they recited תהילים Tehillim for an hour.
There you go. I don't know, not in the time of the
גמרא. Gemara. מי גריסין דטיסני? Mei grisin d'tisa? Okay. מי גריסין, Mei
grisin, water of like barley.
So beans, I keep on saying
barley, beans. מי גריסין של פול Mei grisin shel pol or some
type of a paste of
barley, I did it again, chewed up beans and so on. למימרא
דמסייע ליה לריש לקיש, L'meimra d'mesayei lih l'Resh Lakish, let's say this
supports ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish. דאמר ריש לקיש: D'amar Resh Lakish: רוק
תפל צריך שיהא עם כל אחד ואחד. Rok tapel tzarich sheyehei im
kol echad v'echad. This idea of that tasteless spit, it's not just
its own cleanser, you have to mix it up with all the
other cleansers as well, because we talk about creating a bean paste
by chewing it, so then you're getting your spit into the bean
paste. So he assumes that it's with the other stuff as well,
hopefully it's not through actually putting the other stuff in your mouth
if you think about what some of the other stuff is, but
at least mixing some spit. That's what ריש לקיש Resh Lakish assumed
was true.
Not we're making one solution rather than,
I thought it was seven separate. Separate, but he says with each
of the other items you have to also add a certain amount
of spit.
But spit is its own
thing in and of itself. Yeah, exactly. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so maybe this indicates that because it speaks about chewing the beans.
So the
גמרא Gemara says no, דילמא הבל דפומא מעלי. dilma havla d'puma ma'aly.
No, maybe it's not so much about the spit, maybe it's in
the mouth because somehow the humidity, the you know in the mouth,
the air in the mouth makes a difference, so just because you
want it chewed in your mouth, it's not necessarily because of the
spit, could be other qualities for are achieved that way also. Okay.
מתניתין דלא כרבי יהודה. Matnitin d'lo k'Rabbi Yehuda. Our משנה Mishnah is
not like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דתניא, D'tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא: Baraisa: רבי יהודה אומר מי גריסין רותח ועובר שיתן לתוכו מלח.
Rabbi Yehuda omer mei grisin rotei'ach v'over sheyiten l'tocho melach. It's not
chewed
up bean paste, it's boiling bean paste, and it's before, עובר over
here means before you put into it salt. So yeah, exactly, so
imagine you were making some type of a bean stew, whatever bean
paste, and you had it on the oven and don't put in
the salt yet, that's the thing you have to use. Okay, so
that's not our משנה, Mishnah, our משנה Mishnah didn't speak about the
salt, it didn't speak about boiling, anyway. So now the גמרא Gemara
just clarifies, מאי משמע דהאי עובר לישנא דאקדמויי הוא? Mai mashma d'hai
over lishna d'akdumayei hu? How do you know עובר over means before,
before you put in salt, ועובר. v'over. It should be וכודם, v'kodem,
why ועובר? v'over? Where do you see עובר over means before? So
Michael correctly says, the same way the גמרא's Gemara description of the
word מתנמנם mitnamnem appears multiple times in ש"ס, Shas, this next discussion
also appears multiple times, usually in the context where it says all
ברכות berakhot have to be עובר לעשייתן, over la'asiyatan, before you do
the מצוה. mitzvah. So the word עובר over means before and it's
sometimes... But the, but you know, it's less common that you use
the word עובר over that way. So when it appears, the גמרא
Gemara says, where do you see the word עובר over means before?
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak, אמר קרא, Amar Kra, the פסוק pasuk says, וירץ
אחימעץ דרך הככר ויעבור את הכושי. Vayarotz Achimaatz derech hakikar vayaavor et
hakushi. אחימעץ Achimaatz ran the way of the valley and he passed
in front of the... the כושי. Kushi. So the... what's the translation
of that? Okay.
Ethiopian, I guess, usually. Okay, fine. Anyway, so ויעבור Vayaavor means to
pass in front of. אביי Abaye אמר מהכא amar meihacha from the
following: והוא עבר לפניהם, V'hu avar lifneihem, he passed in front of
them. ואיבעית אימא מהכא: V'iba'it eima meihacha: ויעבור מלכם לפניהם, Vayaavor malkam
lifneihem, their king passed in front of them, וה' בראשם, V'Hashem b'rosham,
and God at their head. Now the problem is that by all
these it more means to pass. It's the combination of the word
pass with לפניהם, lifneihem, pass across, pass in front of them,
pass לפניהם lifneihem in front of them. Right, there was really only
the first פסוק pasuk that did not have the word in front
of where it was implied that we see ויעבור vayaavor means to
go in front. Anyway, so that's how עובר לעשייתן over l'asiyatan and
here before that you put in front of it into its salt.
Okay, so that was the... that was the
דין din phase. מי רגליים שהחמיצו, Meira glai she'chimtzu, urine that has
somehow spoiled. תנא, Tana, כמה חיוצן, kama chyutzan, what does it mean
to become rancid? שלשה ימים, Shlosha yamim, three days it's been left
out.
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, כל שיעורי חכמים בקצמים, kol shiurei
chachamim biktzamim, צריך שיעור לשיעורן, tzarich shiur l'shiuran, it's a great phrase.
All of these quantities of the Rabbis, you know, this amount of
spit and this type of fit and this type of thing, not
enough. You need to give a שיעור shiur for the שיעורן. shiuran.
Okay, what does that mean? So now you think you've solved it.
You've said three day urine. Have you really told me what you
need? Let's take a look. דילד או דזקן, D'yeled o d'zaken, urine
of a child or of an older person? דאיש או דאשה, D'ish
o d'isha, man or a woman? מכוסים או מגולים, Mechusim o megulim,
covered or
exposed? בימות החמה או בימות הגשמים, B'yemos hachama o b'yemos hageshamim, summer
or the winter? So you know none of these things. If you
really want to be precise, there's a lot more details that have
to be figured out.
And it's interesting, like, in other words, let's say this was the
winter. I mean, like you're going to keep it around the whole
summer? Until the summer or the whole fall? That's a good question.
Maybe you had a special storage facility, I don't know. Maybe you
thought it mattered when the urine was procured and not necessarily when
it was used.
And his diet probably as well.
That's interesting also.
It seems to say, like, you know, this wasn't really much used
at that time.
Well, I agree. I think that the point is, as I said
the other day, I don't know of any examples where the גמרא
Gemara actually speaks about this as practical, right? First of all, they
probably couldn't even, you know, could they even really fully identify all
of the seven in their own time? And then the צריך שיעור
לשיעורן tzarich shiur l'shiuran and so on. So I think most of
this discussion was theoretical, which I think is partly the point that's
being made here. Okay, I think the point might be, look, you
know, which also is true, like if you're in a societal context
where like you understand certain things, you don't need it to be
explained to you, right? So whereas if you're coming from like Mars,
you know, you need an enormous amount of detail. So I think
that's partly the point that he's saying. Like, if we were in
the society that we were talking about these seven cleansers, we would
know what it was talking about. But now we're trying to quantify
it and put it down on the books and it's like impossible
to do if you're not in that sort of particular context. Solomon
doesn't like any of this?
I'm sure that he does.
All right, so let's take a look. But I do think that
is his point, like how are we supposed to really know what's
going on here? Okay. וצריך לכסכס שלש פעמים, V'tzarich l'chashkesh shalosh pe'amim,
and you have to rub it each one in three times. איבעיא
רבי ירמיה, Iba'ya Rabbi Yirmiya, אם תבעי דאסבי חד או דילמא אם
תבעי דאסבי תרתי, im tbaei d'asvei chad o dilma im tbaei d'asvei
tartei, and this is also a phrase that comes a couple of
times. I think by אם תבעי דאסבי חד או דילמא אם תבעי
דאסבי תרתי, im tbaei d'asvei chad o dilma im tbaei d'asvei tartei,
מאי? mai? Back and forth, so when you say three, is it
one, two, three, or is it one, two, three? Right? Is each
rub back and forth count as one? תיקו, Teiku, okay, we don't
know. That's another question. Moving on.
העבירן שלא כסדרן, Heviran shelo k'sidran, now if you do them out
of order, it's not good. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, הקדים שניים לראשונים,
hikdim shniyim l'rishonim, now the גמרא, Gemara, as the way רש"י Rashi
reads this, and תוספות Tosafot doesn't disagree, the גמרא Gemara sort of
assumes that there's implicitly two groups here. There's the more natural
stuff, spit, the bean paste, and the urine, and then there's the
more, you know, I don't know, commercial, or whatever, not that I
can call commercial products, but anyway, you
know. Standard cleaners? Yeah, right. But anyway, things that... anyway, but then
the other stuff which is the נתר, neter, the בורית, borit, the
קמוניא, kammonya, the אשלג. ashleg. So there's three that are more your
sort of homegrown products and the others that are less so, and
it puts them in the category of the first group and the
second group. Okay, that's what רש"י Rashi understands what it's referring to.
So
הקדים שניים לראשונים, hikdim shniyim l'rishonim, if you did the second group
before the first group, so does that work or not? Maybe the
order only matters within each group.
So תני חדא שניים עלו לו ראשונים לא עלו לו, tanya chada
shniyim alu lo rishonim lo alu lo, one ברייתא baraita says the
second ones count, not the first ones, ותני אידך, v'tanya idach, another
ברייתא baraita says ראשונים עלו לו שניים לא עלו לו, rishonim alu
lo shniyim lo alu lo, the first ones count and not the
second ones. So how do you reconcile this? So
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אידי ואידי שניים עלו לו ולא ראשונים, aidi
v'aidi shniyim alu lo v'lo rishonim, the second ones count, not the
first. Now the second ones means the second in order
of... Let's take a look. Let's say, okay, this is the first
group, this is the more, I don't know, natural product, this is
the second group, okay, and you did it out of order, so
you did first and then this. So what we're basically saying is
this still works because ignore this and you've done the first three,
right? It should have been one, two, three, four, five, six, seven.
You did four, five, six, seven, one, two, three. So one, two,
three still counts and now you can do four, five, six, seven.
So that's what אביי Abbaye says. So אביי Abbaye says אידי ואידי
שניים עלו. idi v'idi shniim alu. The second ones you did now,
the one, two, three which you did at the
end, that counts, ולא ראשונים, v'lo rishonim, not the four, five, six,
seven which you did first. So that's the version that says the
second ones count. ומאי ראשונים, U'mai rishonim, how about the version that
says the first
ones count? ראשונים כסדרן, Rishonim k'sidran, it means the ones that normally
would be first, one, two, three, ושניים רברסא, v'shniim reversa, but in
this context you did them second. Okay, you got it? So when
normally it should have been like this, you did it like this.
We want to say these one, two, three count. We can describe
it as the second ones count because in the way you did
it now they were the second group, or you could say the
first ones count because they're normally the one, two, three, they're the
ones that normally go first. But the basic point is the same,
the one, two, three counts and then you just do four, five,
six, seven again. Okay, with that we finished most of the discussion
around stains,
and we now really, so both about the idea of, you know,
attributing it, the basic leniencies of review which is the smaller than
a size of a גריס gris or smaller, which we say is
like a penny or a nickel or something of that nature, then
we say if it's on colored garments, which we didn't really explain
why, presumably it's harder to indicate the red, but whatever it is
seems to be an arbitrary exclusion, and finally the idea of the,
color garments and מקבל טומאה, mikabel tumah, only if it's on a
vessel that is מקבל טומאה mikabel tumah or a person who obviously
is also טמא. tamei. So those are the basic leniencies and now
we move on, and again the last discussion was about using various
cleansers to get rid of it or to get it to a
state where it's no longer a problem. Incubating and all that. Right,
etc. And now we move on to moving to the next discussion,
which is a very important discussion in הלכות נדה. Hilchos Niddah. Each
one of these things we've been doing the last few days till
the end of the מסכת masechet are very critical for practical הלכות
נדה. Hilchos Niddah. So one of the whole areas stains, stains occur
all the time, whole issue about, you know, wearing sometimes colored underwear
if for someone who's staining a lot, this is sometimes a way
of dealing with those issues for things that we said and determining
the difference between when is it a stain where you have those
leniencies and when is it a ראיה, reiah, the whole הלכה halacha
of שמואל Shmuel about הרגשה, hargashah, that's one very critical area of
נדה. Niddah. Now we move on to another which has to do
with וסתות, vestos, which is when a woman expects to get her
period. We have seen that before, mostly in the context of when
she bleeds at a time she's expecting her period she doesn't have
to worry twenty-four hours back, those were the concerns at the beginning
of the מסכת, masechet, but the other critical issues that are applied
to us today is the time she's expecting to get her period
she has to do an internal check to see whether it's occurred,
and she's not allowed to have sex that entire period of time
because you don't want that would be irresponsible, you might turn out
to be a נדה niddah in the middle of having sex. So
for the first though there is so we have to figure out
how do you determine when are those periods that you're expecting when
is that time that you're expecting to get her period? So let's
take a look now at the משנה. mishnah. כל אשה שיש לה
וסת דיה שעתה. Kol ishah sheyeish lah veset dayah sha'atah.
Any woman right that has a וסת, veset, a regular time of
seeing, it's enough when she saw, meaning when she then bleeds during
the time she's expected, she doesn't have to say oh maybe it
started up to twenty-four hours ago because no, this is exactly when
you're expected to get it, this is when it happened. Okay, so
that's in terms of the issues of the beginning of the מסכת
masechet which are not so relevant for us today. ואלו הן הוסתות.
V'eilu hein havesatos. Now we get to be very relevant because as
I said there are other aspects of וסתות vestos which are very
applicable today. So these are the וסתות, vestatos, the periods that she's
the experiences or whatever the things that let her know she's expecting
to get her period. We're in the second משנה. mishnah. I know,
well whatever. מפהקת, Mipahakes, if she basically
yawns like a whole yawning fit comes out her,
או מעטשת, o meatashes, sneezes, וחוששת בפי כריסה, v'chosheshas b'fi k'reisah, she
has a sensation like some types of cramping in her stomach area,
ובשיפולי מעיה, u'v'shippulei mei'eha, or it's more towards at the bottom of
her stomach, you know, area, so either like at the top of
the stomach or the bottom of the stomach, more in the groin
area, ושופעת, v'shofaas, or if she is bleeding, literally she's of course
if she's bleeding what does it mean it's a
וסת? veset? That she's
a נדה. niddah. So the גמרא Gemara will talk about that. וכמין
צמרמורות אוחזין אותה, U'k'min tzimarmoros ochezin osah, or she has various certain
types of cramps, all these types of things, וכן כיוצא בזה, v'chein
kayotzei bazei, all of these types of things. וכל שקבעה לה שלשה
פעמים הרי זה וסת. V'chol shekav'ah lah shloshah pe'amim harei zeh veset.
If she has it three times, that is a וסת. veset. Now
Michael is a little surprised because until now and normally when וסתות
vestos are taught we talk about them in the context of a
certain cycle. A woman sees every twenty-five days, every twenty-eight days, every
thirty days and so on. Yes, and that is how וסתות vestos
are taught to the point that that's called the וסת הימים. veset
hayamim. To the point that the other וסתות... vestos... this משנה Mishna
mentions and I should point out that this משנה Mishna mentions it,
this משנה Mishna mentions it as if this is the primary וסת
Vesset which is called the וסת הגוף Vesset HaGuf which is actually
probably for a lot of women who are not so regular in
terms of the days, some very much could be a greater predictor
of when they are going to get it, which is a certain
type of bodily experience that is a predictor that you're about to
get your period. Okay so so these types of things that oh
I always get I feel these cramps, I know I'm going to
get my period in the next 24 hours. I know I'm going
to get my period usually a few hours later. Very often there
are women who can tell that. Now sometimes you know it's not
so you know you don't know it's not a very specific feeling,
you don't really know exactly from the time that feeling begins when
the period is going to come, but there are times where if
women
pay attention to their bodies they can actually see, you know they
might know anyway, but certainly if they stop to sort of pay
attention realize that there are certain bodily experiences that could be good
predictors. And so again sneezing does not just mean a normal sneezing,
you know everybody says sneezing. Like there's a sneezing fit, there's a
coughing fit, there's a yawning—yeah you got a really really
whatever
some types of thing that is predictors. Now they also say you
cannot too much abstract it, and you know obviously you can't just
say yeah some weird things happen to me in my body at
a certain period of time. It has to be something like pretty
specific, you know, and unusual, not like you know I happened to
sneeze, okay, but it has to be like specific and unusual, specific
and unusual
and a good predictor and it predicts three times in a row
and that establishes a וסת הגוף. Vesset HaGuf. And I actually
you know both when I teach this in ישיבה Yeshiva and I
speak to כלות Kallos and I speak to כלה Kalla teachers or
whatever I you know I talk a lot about I—this is like
a הלכה Halacha that has almost been forgotten, that this is a
וסת, Vesset, but according to this משנה Mishna we'll see in the
גמרא Gemara it's maybe the primary וסת, Vesset, and it's something that
you know has to be retaught because so many women spend so
much time like doing this whole complicated calendar thing, and if you
know the details of וסתות Vessetos and וסת שאינו קבוע Vesset She’eino
Kavuah it leads to three different times during the month you have
to be worried, and at the end of the day it's A,
highly complicated and B, not a good predictor. And this is very
straightforward, it's about women getting in touch with their own bodies, and
it can be a very good predictor. So this is really a—and
if you have this וסת Vesset you don't have to worry about
the other one. So this is an area of וסתות Vessetos which
often is gets overlooked which I think is very very you know
central to this to the idea and according to as the גמרא
Gemara we're going to see in this משנה Mishna basically stands it's
like this is how it describes what a וסת Vesset is as
the primary one. So let's take a look at what the גמרא
Gemara says.
You're saying that the calendar one is maybe secondary, that if you
don't have these then that—exactly, exactly.
So first of all the way it's framed in the משנה, Mishna,
אלו הן הוסתות, Eilu Hen HaVessetos, right, and it doesn't even mention
the the period of days. And the גמרא Gemara will actually say
there might be a הלכה Halacha difference, that you might be able
to establish this one with fewer recurrences than
the calendar—this says three
times—this says three times, but let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. Okay, it's certainly not worse, and probably better than the calendar
one. And anyway, whenever you have one וסת Vesset you don't have
to worry about others, so you should certainly try to see if
you can establish this one.
גמרא. Gemara. סלקא דעתך? Salka Da'atach? תנינא חדא זימנא, Tnina Chada Zimna,
we already taught this, כל—the first the basic principle, the first part
of the משנה, Mishna. כל אשה שיש לה וסת דיה שעתה, Kol
Isha SheYesh Lah Vesset Dayah Sha'atah, a woman who has a regular
period doesn't have to worry about 24 hours back, that was the
first משנה. Mishna But says no. התם בוסתות דיומי הכא בוסתות דגופא.
Hatam BeVessetos DeYomei Hacha BeVessetos DeGufa. Right, there it was talking about
maybe a a cycle of days, a period of days. Here the
משנה Mishna is very clear, it's coming to introduce this idea of
the וסת Vesset of the גוף, Guf, of bodily experiences. כדיתני KediTani
and then it
explains אלו הן הוסתות המפהק והמעטש והחוששת בפי כריסה ובשיפולי מעיה ובשופעת
Eilu Hen HaVessetos HaMefahek VeHaMe’atesh VeHaChosheshet BeFi Kresa UBeShiphulei Me’eha UBeShofaat etc.
So the point of this משנה Mishna is not to introduce the
rule that a וסת Vesset is דיה שעתה. Dayah Sha'atah. The point
of this משנה Mishnah is to introduce that this is a וסת,
Vesset, a וסת הגוף, Vesset HaGuf, bodily experiences. Is that הרגשה Hargasha
that we used in the
previous—so that's a good question.
Is the הרגשה Hargasha that שמואל Shmuel was talking about this type
of menstrual cramping? So there is an opinion that says yes, mostly
the answer is mostly the ראשונים Rishonim פוסקים Poskim
say no because this is talking about it coming before and being
a predictor, and שמואל Shmuel is talking about at the time and
being part of what defines the the sort of experience of bleeding.
But it is a possibility, the רמב"ם Rambam seems to indicate that
those might be the same or similar. Okay so the גמרא Gemara
says,
שופעת, Shofaat, השופעת ואזלה? HaShofaat VeAzla? You know, flowing, so she's flowing,
she's bleeding, what do you mean a predictor? It's happening! Maybe she's
cold. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר עולא בריה דרב עילאי, Amar
Ulla Brei DeRav Ilai, so עולא Ulla son of רב עילאי Rav
Ilai says, בשופעת דם טמא מתוך דם טהור. BeShofaat Dam Tamei Mitoch
Dam Tahor.
She actually first she gets טהור Tahor blood and then it's followed
by טמא Tamei blood. What's טהור Tahor blood? So טהור Tahor blood
could be let's say the color isn't problematic, first she gets brown
or yellow staining, and that comes 12 hours before she actually gets
the red staining and her actual period, that could be used as
a וסת. Vesset. Now this actually
is— also a serious possibility of establishing a וסת veset, *veset*, which
interestingly is not discussed so much in the פוסקים poskim *poskim* but
is right here in the גמרא Gemara *gemara*, where a woman basically
says, can often say, I spot before I get my period. When
she's spotting, she's not yet a נידה *niddah*. Why? Because those spots,
A, they might not be red, and B, they might be small.
So I get small spots before my period, maybe she's even wearing
colored underwear, which she wears in the period before she becomes a
נידה *niddah*. Right? You only the מנהג *minhag* of white underwear is
once she's counting her שבעה נקיים *shiv'ah nekiyim*. So she gets these
spots, she's not a נידה *niddah*, right? But can it, but maybe
it always occurs 12 hours, 24 hours before I actually get my
period or before they're big enough or whatever it is. So again,
that I think is definitely a basis for establishing a וסת הגוף
veset ha-guf, *veset haguf*, but it's very interesting that you don't find
it so much in the פוסקים poskim *poskim*.
Can we combine these bodily signs to times and say, you know,
I get it, I've seen it, and then like a week later
or three days later, depending on the time, you know, I get
my... can we do that? Do they say she wouldn't?
What you're saying is that let's say she gets random spotting, mid-month
spotting, would you say, oh well, you've got a וסת veset, *veset*,
now you have to worry 12 hours later even though it happened
mid-month? Or do you sort of say, you know, the spotting that
occurs after at least 25 days have passed since my last period?
Yeah, you probably would want to combine that. That probably is true.
But you don't need to. The interesting thing about these וסתות הגוף
vestos ha-guf *vestot haguf* in the פוסקים poskim *poskim* like the שולחן
ערוך *Shulchan Aruch* is that in principle it can be established independent
of time. Right. Logically it is connected to time as well and
you could probably create a hybrid. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara *gemara* goes on. דכמין צמרודות *d'k'min tzimrudot*, certain
types of various like a sort of cramping, וכיוצא בהן *v'khayozei bahen*,
and
anything similar. לאתויי מאי *l'atuyei mai*, so what would this include? אמר
רבה בר עולא *amar Rabbah bar Ulla*, לאתויי הרגשת ראשה כבד עליה
*l'atuyei hargashat roshah kaved aleha*, a woman that has a feeling of
like a heaviness in the head, ואיבריה כבדים עליה *v'eivareiha kvedim aleha*,
a feeling of a heaviness of her limbs of her body, רותתת
*rotetat*,
or she has feverish, רותתת *rotetat*, oh I'm sorry, you're right, I
misread that. So
I saw רותחת *rotachat* and feverish. רותתת *rotetat*, I'm not sure.
Trembling it says. Okay. So some form of trembling.
Oh like מירתת *mirtat*, right, right. Okay fine. Okay so trembling. וגוסה
*v'gosah*, or belching. So any various other types of sensations. All of
these things, again, if they're specific and predictive, then they are count,
then they could be a וסת veset *veset*. אמר רב הונא בר
חייא אמר שמואל Shmuel *amar Rav Huna bar Chiyya amar Shmuel*, הרי
אמרו לימים שנים *harei amru l'yamim shenayim*. There was a teaching that
says that if it's a וסת veset *veset* of days, you need
it to be repeated two times. Days means like 28 days, 25
days, you know, a certain daily, or you know, how, a gap
of days. לוסתות אחד *l'vestot echad*. For the וסתות vestos *vestot*, meaning
the things we mentioned in our משנה Mishnah. *mishnah*, only one occurrence
is enough of a predictor. And that sounds crazy. One of anything
could be a chance. But the point I want to make though
at this stage before we get on is, number one, notice he
calls the day one ימים yamim *yamim*, he calls the bodily one
וסתות vestos. *vestot*. So in terms of which is seen as the
primary, similar to our משנה Mishnah *mishnah*, איזהו וסת veset *eizehu veset*?
And the bodily one, he says he's less repeat, actually no repeat,
than the day one. Now by the way though, that might not
be actually fully accurate because as the גמרא Gemara *gemara* will point
out, you can't really have a gap of days without two points,
right? If it's every 28 days, you need to see one and
then see again 28 days. So when he says the day means
two, does it mean two times you've bled, the beginning point and
the end point, or does he mean a repeat? One gap of
28 days and then another gap of 28 days. So anyway, but
it certainly seems like the emphasis is is that the bodily experiences
is more predictive and needs fewer repeats, even once, which is no
repeat.
But the first line of the גמרא Gemara *gemara* said they're both
וסת veset. *veset*, one is וסת הימים veset ha-yamim, *veset ha-yamim*.
I know, and it also says our משנה Mishnah *mishnah* says שלושה
*sheloshah*. But here we are actually making a hierarchy. Okay. למה שלא
מנו חכמים שלושה *le-mah shelo manu chachamim sheloshah*, things not on the
list,
three, דהוה אמינא שלושה *d'hava amina shloshah*, that would require three times.
That would be less predictive and would require three times. So seems
like the bodily stuff is the most predictive, the days is the
secondary, there are other signs so you need more times, and things
not on the list also can work but you need three times.
למה שלא מנו חכמים לאתויי מאי *le-mah shelo manu chachamim l'atuyei mai*,
what does that include, things not on the list? So אמר רב
יוסף *amar Rav Yosef*, לאתויי ראשה כבד עליה ואיבריה כבדים עליה ורותתת
וגוסה *l'atuyei roshah kaved aleha v'eivareiha kvedim aleha v'rotetat v'gosah*, רותתת *rotetat*,
I just did it again, וגוסה *v'gosah*, the list as we just
said, heavy feeling in the head, in the bones,
tremors, belching and so on. Those are not as predictive but that
can also work. אמר ליה אביי *amar lei Abaye*, we'll get to
the משנה Mishnah *mishnah* in a minute. אמר ליה אביי מאי קא
משמע לן Kamashma lan, מתניתין היא *amar lei Abaye mai ka mashma
lan matnitin hi*. Then why what are you telling us? You know,
that's in our משנה Mishnah *mishnah*. דקתני וכן כל כיוצא בהן *d'katani
v'chen kol khayozei bahen*, and ופירשה רבה בר עולא *u-fiershah Rabbah bar
Ulla*, and רבה בר עולא *Rabbah bar Ulla* said that it meant
exactly this list. Now it's a bit of a funny question. Just
because רבה בר עולא *Rabbah bar Ulla* said it meant that list
doesn't mean שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* doesn't have to say that list. And
maybe more than. of that is that שמואל is saying that it
has a different status. The first stuff in the משנה Mishnah. is
only once, these things are three times, so, you know, it's a
חידוש chiddush too, what שמואל is saying does seem to be a
חידוש. chiddush. Number one, he's once again telling us list, and number
two, telling us it has less of a status than the first
part of the משנה. Mishnah. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara somehow feels that
no, that wouldn't be what שמואל was telling us. So the גמרא
Gemara says אלא
אמר אביי לאתויי אכלה שום וראתה אכלה בצלים וראתה כסא דפלפלין וראתה.
ela amar Abaye le'asuyei achla shum ve-ra'atah achla betzalim ve-ra'atah
kissa de-pilpelin ve-ra'atah. Let's say she ate garlic and then she had
her period, or onions, or she chewed pepper, and not pepper like
red pepper, pepper like peppercorns, and she had her period. That would
also be a type of a וסת, veset, but that is less
predictive and would require three times. Now, what category is that called?
This is important in terms of just labeling. The משנה Mishnah is
called basically וסת הגוף, Veset Haguf, things of bodily experiences, the day
period is called וסת veset הימים, this is called וסת מעשה, veset
ma'aseh, which basically means she did something and then she saw. But
it's not exactly a וסת מעשה, veset ma'aseh, because there's another וסת
המעשה veset ha-ma'aseh which is like,
if you remember the גמרא Gemara discussed like jumping up and down.
And there the גמרא Gemara said that that only works in combination
with days, it doesn't work by itself. So תוספות Tosafot basically explains
the difference. And תוספות Tosafot says in that case, it really is
that the external sort of shock or not trauma, but what's the
word? Anyway, impact, you know, causes bleeding, and that is, you know,
not really a natural way the body works, and even though it's
your תמיד tamid because we say even מחמת אונס, machmat ones, still
that's not so much of a וסת, veset you need to combine
it with days and so on. This he says is what happens,
you eat the pepper, it causes some bodily change inside of your
body, and ultimately then it indirectly leads to the releasing of the
blood. But it's not like the physical impact, it's like
the hormones and the chemicals in the body, that's more natural once
it interacts and therefore he says that works without a combination of
days, and this is a different type of a like וסת המעשה
veset ha-ma'aseh not like the other one. Now what's important about all
of
this—and it needs three times?
This according to this needs three times. The תוספות דאכלה שום Tosafot
d'achla shum where he describes the difference. He says here, if you
want to look at the end of תוספות Tosafot he says like
this: דכל שתקפה מחמת אונס אפילו כמה זמנים לא קבע. de-kol she-tikfaf
machmat ones afilu kama zmanim lo kava.
He says like this, דכל שתקפה de-kol she-tikfaf after the parentheses in
the תוספות אכלה שום, Tosafot achla shum, דכל שתקפה מחמת אונס אפילו
כמה זמנים לא קבע. de-kol she-tikfaf machmat ones afilu kama zmanim lo
kava. If it's because of some external force,
it doesn't become a וסת veset by itself, only in combination with
days. אבל אכלה שום לא חשיב אונס, aval achla shum lo chashiv
ones, it's not an external force, כמו דתרפצה, k'mo de-tarfitchi, like jumping
up and down. שאין הראייה באה ידי טורח אלא ממילא. she-ein ha-re'iyah
ba'ah yedei torach ela mi-meila. It's not coming because the impact somehow
caused the blood to discharge, it's eventually coming because of what's going
on inside of your body. You just introduced this thing that caused
your body to function in a certain way. Now the reason this
is interesting is because with the introduction of the birth control pill,
which is
totally—okay, sometimes there's spotting, but pretty much is pretty darn predictable about
when you're going to bleed when you go off the pill, the
active pill, a certain amount of days after you go off the
active pill. By the way, it's important to frame it that way,
because it's not like, oh, I'm on the pill, I see every
thirty days, because actually it's not really a function of thirty days,
it's a function of when you stop taking the active pill, and
sometimes women will take more, like you're going on a vacation, you
want to not be a נדה niddah and so on, you know,
whatever, just some women in general spread it out and do it
once every two months or once every three months, and it's really
a function of the last time you take the active pill and
then the bleeding usually occurs sometimes like somewhere like two days later.
So for each woman it's a little different. So can you establish
a וסת veset x number of days after I stop taking the
active pill, x number of hours or whatever. So basically the פוסקים
say yes, there's a question about how often you have to repeat
it and so on, but then they ask the question like which
category do we put it in? Okay, so the
category—yeah, so basically it's the closest. Some of them put it in
that category. Now there of course it's different, there the peppers are
causing, here the pill is preventing and then you go off the
pill, but at least it's something similar, something you're ingesting that's interacting
with your hormones and your body. A lot of פוסקים say we
don't even need to put it in a category, it's clear that
it's a predictor and so on, and then you know, and but
that is a very major question these days about determining וסתות vestos.
in relationship to the pill. Yes.
There was a plant in the Mediterranean that's now extinct, known in
ancient times, that was used as a contraceptive. Aha. And I think
it was probably as a hormonal contraceptive plant. Fascinating. Any discussion of
that?
Not that I know of. The גמרא's Gemara. only knowledge about contraception
other than some type of a nonsurgical type of a thing or
whatever. Sometimes the גמרא Gemara actually does talk about taking some type
of a potion of some type of a what's the word?
Not potion, but
whatever,
anyway, ingesting something.
Yeah, no, no, no, no. In the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* the only type of temporary,
you know, what do you call it, birth control that gets discussed
is the מוך *moch*, which is some type of a, you know,
sponge. Okay, anyway, so that's the background. Now of course these three
categories are not in the משנה Mishnah. *Mishna*. The משנה mishna *Mishna*
always discusses three times. This is some are one, some are two,
some are three. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to
help to clarify them. Let's take a look.
So that's like Michael's question too, like, you know, if you eat
peppers and you didn't bleed, but when you ate peppers around the
time of your period you did, then the וסת veset. *vesset* would
be set. Okay, so we see it's not based on one cause,
it's based on two causes and then your וסת veset, *vesset* would
be a hybrid וסת *vesset*. So that would be correct. Yeah, so
it's true that most of these certainly those types of things of
the peppers and the onions you imagine, although in principle don't have
to be established together with days, in practice would be because if
you did it during the rest of the month it wouldn't have
the same effect. Okay, so now let's see what the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says. So now though we have a list of days of
three, two and one that's different than our משנה mishna *Mishna* that
says everything is three. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this,
אמר רב יוסף *Amar Rav Yosef*, where were we?
Okay, אמר רב יוסף *Amar Rav Yosef*, so רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*
said in response to this statement of אביי *Abaye* about the peppers
and the garlic, לא שמיע לי הא שמעתא *Lo shemiya lei ha
shema'ta*. I've never heard this teaching before. You remember of course that
רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* got ill and forgot a lot of the
things that he had taught. So אמר ליה אביי *Amar lei Abaye*,
so אביי *Abaye* who was the student said back to him, את
מניתה ניהלן *At manita nialan*, you told it to us. ואהא מניתה
ניהלן *Ve'aha manita nialan*, and on the following you taught it to
us. We have the following teaching which is היתה למודה *Hayta limuda*,
it's the coming up משנה mishna *Mishna*. היתה למודה להיות רואה יום
חמישה עשר ושינתה ליום עשרים *Hayta limuda lihyot ro'ah yom chamisha asar
veshinata leyom esrim*. A woman used to see every fifteen days and
now she switched to every twenty days. By the way, there's a
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that has a problem with it because every fifteen
is during the זבה *zava* period and it's very unusual anyway. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it really means every fifteen days since
going to the מקוה *mikvah*, really means every twenty-two days. Anyway, just
to make it a little more realistic. But regardless, a woman sees
every fifteen days and now she starts, one month she saw after
twenty days. Then this at certain the next month she can't have
sex on day fifteen or on day twenty because you're now in
some middle state. You don't know, maybe you're moving to a twenty-day
cycle, so twenty days could be a problem, but maybe you're still
on your fifteen. You had a very established pattern of fifteen. So
you have to worry for both until it resolves itself. What?
All the days in
between?
Yes, and we're going to discuss that again. Now שלש פעמים ליום
עשרים *Shalosh pe'amim leyom esrim*, if she switched three times consecutively over
to day twenty, three establishes the, you know, the pattern. So הותר
יום חמישה עשר *Hutar yom chamisha asar*, then fifteen is made permissible,
meaning it no longer is your cycle. ונקבע יום עשרים *Venikba yom
esrim*, and now you only worry about day twenty as established, now
you know that's your cycle. שאין אשה קובעת לה וסת עד שתקבענה
שלש פעמים *She'ein isha kova'at la vesset ad shetikba'ena shalosh pe'amim*. A
woman does not establish a וסת *vesset* until she does it three
times. So again, the משנה *Mishna* we just read before said by
the bodily, said three times. The coming up משנה *Mishna* is going
to talk about days and say three times. So where do you
get this one, two and three? All these משניות mishnayos. *Mishnayot* are
talking about three. So אביי *Abaye* says to רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*,
on this משנה *Mishna* you made the following comment. ואמרת לן עלה
*Ve'amarta lan alah*, you said to us on this משנה *Mishna*, אמר
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda? אמר שמואל *Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel*, said
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda, *Rav Yehuda* in the name of שמואל *Shmuel*,
זו דברי רבן גמליאל בר רבי Rabban Gamliel bar Rebbi שאמר משום
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel *Zu divrei Rabban Gamliel
bar Rabbi she'amar mishum Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*. This is the position
of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel בר רבי Rebbi *Rabban Gamliel bar Rabbi*
who says in the name of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel? *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*. How we know I don't know,
presumably by tradition, but all of these teachings of three times, this
is the position of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel?
*Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*. אבל חכמים אומרים *Aval chachamim omrim*, but the
sages say, וסת אינה צריכה Tsricha, לא לשנות ולא לשלש *Vesset einah
tzericha lo lishnot velo leshalesh*. If you see, you do not have
to do it two or three times, that's not necessary. All this
requirement of three times is all רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel. *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*. ואמינא לך *Ve'amina lach*, and we
said to you, לשנות אמרת לן לשלש מיבעיא *Lishnot amarta lan leshalesh
mibaya*? If you don't have to do it twice, according to the
חכמים *chachamim*, of course you don't have to do it three times.
What do you mean you don't have to do it two or
three times? ואמרת לן *Ve'amarta lan*, and here's how you explained it
to us, לשנות בווסתות לשלש בימים *Lishnot bevessatot
leshalesh beyamim*. When it comes to the וסתות vestos *vessatot*, which again
means the וסת הגוף Veset Haguf *vesset haguf*, the bodily things, the
cramps and so on, you don't even have to do it twice,
even once is enough. If it comes to the spacing of the
days, then you don't have to do it three times, two times
is enough. Okay, nice little פשט pshat, *pshat*, right? לא לשנות ולא
לשלש *Lo lishnot velo leshalesh*. Some things you don't even have to
do twice, nothing you have to do three times, once or twice
is enough depending on the thing. So here we have now that
our משנה *Mishna* that says three is רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*. There's another opinion out there
that says no, actually less than three. If it's the bodily things
once, if it's the day things twice. Maybe if it's the peppers
and the garlic that's three, but mostly one or two is enough.
Now what is this debate about? There's a classic debate of רבי
Rebbi *Rebbi* and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel *Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel* by חזקה *chazaka*. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* says a חזקה *chazaka* is only
established after three times and רבי Rebbi *Rebbi* says the חזקה *chazaka*
is established after two times. Okay, and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* actually
in יבמות *Yevamot* says sometimes. sometimes we פוסקין pasken like one, sometimes
we פוסקין like the other, there's things about establishing like your pattern
about bleeding, it could be an issue about how often my ox
gores so to like establish that it's a regular gorer, all these
various types of issues, what establishes a pattern? So it seems what
the גמרא Gemara, is saying is רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel says three is very formalistic, it's always three. רבי Rebbi
who says two, at least according to this understanding, is more flexible.
He says normally two, but maybe sometimes even one, maybe sometimes three,
you know, and that is the position of רבי Rebbi, and that's
the position not being represented here in these משניות. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara, now says ונימא זו דברי רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, ve-neima
zu divrei Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, why don't you just say this
is רבן שמעון בן גמליאל? Why did you say it's רבן גמליאל
בר רבי Rebbi. who says in the name of רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל? הא קמשמע לן שמואל דרבן גמליאל שמואל שמואל סבר דרבן גמליאל
בר רבי כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל סבירא ליה, ha-kamasmalan Shmuel d'Rabban Gamliel,
Shmuel Shmuel sivar d'Rabban Gamliel bar Rebbi k'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel sevira
lei, that רבן גמליאל the son of רבי Rebbi holds like רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל. So it's a little funny. The משנה that's being
edited often by רבי Rebbi is presents the סתם stam position not
of רבי, of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל of three times. And even
רבי'ס Rebbi's grandson, רבן גמליאל בר רבי בן רבי Rabban Gamliel bar
Rebbi ben Rebbi holds like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל of three times.
Three times does tend to be basically our פסק psak as well,
not רבי'ס Rebbi's פסק psak of two. Okay, so all these משנות
mishnas say three but there's a possibility of less according to רבי.
And again what it reflects is the idea, and what you see
from this again is that the וסתות הגוף vestos haguf, are assumed
to be more standard, more predictive than the other וסתות.
vesta’os Now there's just one question. Yeah. So רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
is saying no matter what sign it is, always three? Be it
גוף, guf, be it days, be it
peppers?
Exactly. And that's why the משנה said three, that was גוף. guf.
The משנה we're about to read by ימים says three.
All that is רבן שמעון בן גמליאל who says three.
This idea of distinguishing between the type of וסת is a רבי
position. It's interesting to me you usually, I mean, you'd think a
סתם משנה stam Mishnah would be like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So
they're not bringing him in here at all?
That's true, not every סתם משנה stam Mishnah is like רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir doesn't have an opinion or whatever.
But there's a whole bunch of them now.
Yeah, but not in this debate about three or two. So anyway,
but it is interesting that רבי himself is not representing his own
position as the סתם. stam. Yes. Okay, so let's take a look
at the next משנה. Now we move on to days. And as
I said before, days tends to be the focus of all of
the פוסקים and all of the כלה kallah classes and part of
the reason is because the discussion about days is much more complicated
and much more details-oriented and maybe also a little bit more quantifiable.
Again, the whole issue about the about the cramping and the you
know and so on, the bodily ones are much more subjective. How
much cramping? And you can't put it in a הלכה halacha as
much and it much more requires the woman's own subjective experience. So
the day thing is the one that gets much more discussed and
formalized and that's what we're going to move into right now. הייתה
למודה להיות רואה בתחילת הוסת, Haysa lemuda lihyos ro'a b'tchilas ha-veset, she
normally would see at the beginning of the וסתות. We're still by
the way, after that introduction we're still in this stage, still assuming
the beginning of the,
we're still assuming that it's a bodily experience. So let's say she
would start getting a sneezing fit. And then we know that normally
the sneezing fit would go on for an hour, but she would
normally start her cycle within the first 20 minutes of the sneezing
fit. So then כל הטהרות שעשתה בתוך הוסת טמאות. kol ha-taharos she'asa
b'toch ha-veset tme'os. Then anything that she did during that sneezing fit,
you know, if eventually she saw sometime that she had blood that
she was a נדה, niddah, that's all problematic because we assume that
it occurred, we said you don't have to go back 24 hours,
right? But if you normally start at the beginning of the sneezing
fit, you do have to assume it began at the beginning of
the sneezing fit and everything is a problem. רבי
יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yose omer, okay so that's that. או בסוף הוסת,
O be-sof ha-veset, let's say she was, let's say she normally see
at the end of the sneezing fit and lo and behold she
did see at the end of the sneezing fit, then כל הטהרות
שעשתה בתוך הוסת טהורות. kol ha-taharos she'asa b'toch ha-veset tehoros. Then she
can assume whatever she saw, she saw just now and that she
doesn't have to worry about the stuff at the beginning of the
sneezing fit because it normally would not begin then, would normally begin
towards the end. So that is the end of the discussion about
the about the גוף guf and now we move into the days.
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, this stage should have been the previous משנה.
Yeah I know. So sometimes the way the משנה is divided up
by the way was a more decision of the publisher and not
of the גמרא. Gemara, Okay. And there's no also and there's no
גמרא Gemara on this last line. So you don't know if that
right which you could just as easily have kept it to the
previous משנה. But רבי יוסי'ס Rabbi Yose's statement though is a little
bit in reference to this, so the context helps. רבי יוסי אומר
אף ימים ושעות וסתות. Rabbi Yose omer af yamim ve-sha'os vestot. Even
days and hours can be a וסת. Now again even days can
be a וסת, at first sounds like the whole idea of the
day gap like 28 days or whatever is a חידוש chidush of
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, but the גמרא doesn't understand it that way.
It understands that his point is is that not that the idea
that you can establish a pattern based on days, 28, 25 whatever,
that's taken for granted. What רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is saying is
the entire day can be the time that you have to be
off-limits. Okay let's see how this gets explained. הייתה למודה להיות רואה
עם הנץ החמה, Haysa lemuda lihyos ro'a im hanetz hachama, אינה אסורה
אלא עם הנץ החמה. eina asura ela im hanetz hachama. So רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose says not only can a day be a period
but his real חידוש chidush is שעות, sha'os, hours. So let's say
a woman always saw every 28 days at sunrise, you know, so
she's only forbidden during sunrise. not before sunrise, not after sunrise, you
can be very precise. The same way in a וסת הגוף, veset
haguf the sneezing fit, you could say beginning of the fit or
end of the fit, you don't have to say the whole sneezing
fit, you can subdivide it, so even when it's about a
day-to-sort of pattern, you can say, okay, during this hour is when
you see. You can subdivide, that's the אף. af. Day-day וסתות work
like וסת הגוף veset haguf, and you can have a specific period
within the day. רבי יהודה אומר כל היום שלה. Rabbi Yehuda omer
kol hayom shelah. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is more strict and we
rule like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. He says no, I'm sorry, when
you're no longer about the body, when you're talking about a day
pattern, then the whole day has to be off-limits. We'll see in
the גמרא what that means, but you cannot just say this one
hour and we basically rule like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So let's
see what the גמרא says.
Do we usually rule like רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda?
I don't remember. תנא, Tanna, כיצד, keitzad, okay, כיצד אמר רבי יוסי
ימים ושעות וסתות? keitzad amar Rabbi Yosi yamim vesha'os vestos? In what
way does רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi say you go by days and
hours? הייתה למידה להיות רואה מיום עשרים ליום עשרים ומשש שעות לשש
שעות. Hayeta lemuda lihyot ro'ah miyom esrim leyom esrim umishesh sha'os leshesh
sha'os. She would see every 20 days at, you know, and in
the sixth hour, at 11:00 AM. Okay? So again, that's the ימים
ושעות, yamim vesha'os, right? It's not just she sees at 11:00 AM.
She sees at 11:00 AM every 20 days. It's a specific hour
within a day pattern.
Okay? So הגיע יום עשרים ולא ראתה. higgia yom esrim velo ra'ata.
Now day 20 began and it was great, right? She hasn't seen
yet. אסור לשמש כל שש שעות ראשונות דברי רבי יהודה. assur leshamesh
kol shesh sha'os rishonot divrei Rabbi Yehuda. רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, since she normally sees at 11:00 AM on
day 20, every, you know, from sunrise until 11:00 AM is all
off-limits because it's all part of the same day that she normally
is going to see. What about afterwards? We'll talk in a minute.
רבי יוסי מתיר עד שש שעות. Rabbi Yosi matir ad shesh sha'os.
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says, you know what, until 11:00 she's fine.
וחוששת בשש שעות. Vechosheshet beshesh sha'os. But she does have to worry
during the eleventh hour. From 11:00 to 12:00, that's normally when she
sees on day 20, so she's off-list, she's אסורה asura from
11:00 until 12:00. עברו שש שעות ולא ראתה. avru shesh sha'os velo
ra'ata. Now the sixth hour is over, it's now 12:00. אסור לשמש
כל היום כולו דברי רבי יהודה.
assur leshamesh
kol
hayom kulo divrei Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says she's still
forbidden the entire rest of the day. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
the units you use are day units. Now, not day 24-hour days,
basically what's called an עונה onah unit, which is either daytime or
nighttime. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says if she sees during the
day, she's אסורה asura the whole daytime period. If she sees at
night, she's אסורה asura the whole nighttime period. Before, during, after the
time that she normally sees, you cannot be taper it down into
hour units, you have to work with day units. That's what רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. רבי יוסי מתיר מן המנחה ולמעלה. Rabbi Yosi
matir min hamincha ulema'ala. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says I don't agree.
She's אסורה asura during the hour she sees, before and after she's
okay and from מנחה mincha on. Now מנחה mincha here means מנחה
גדולה, mincha gedola, which means basically, you know, 12:30. So the question
is why 12:30, not 12:00? So רש"י Rashi says technically you could
actually דאוון daven מנחה mincha from 12:00, we just say 12:30 because
to play it safe. תוספות Tosafot says no, maybe you really do
have to wait till 12:30, you're not allowed, you can't דאוון daven
מנחה, mincha, you know, even in theory you can't. But nevertheless, so
okay, maybe רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi adds an extra half hour here.
But regardless, רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosi basic position is you can go
by unit hours. So when it comes to וסתות הגוף, vesta’os ha-guf.
it's clear you could talk about beginning of the period, end of
the period. When it comes to the day cycle, again, I think
it once again shows that the וסת הגוף is a greater predictor.
If it's a וסת הגוף, everybody seems to agree you could say
beginning of the sneezing, end of the sneezing, we're comfortable with that.
But if it's every 20 days, every 25 days, you know, there's
a certain amount of variation. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says no,
no, no, I'm okay there being very precise and saying one hour
is off, the hour that has been your pattern, and רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says I have to give you a little bit more
of a bigger unit because I assume a certain amount of variation.
And we rule like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So when a woman
establishes a וסת based on a pattern of a cycle of days,
then the entire if she sees in the daytime, then the entire
daytime she's אסור assur to have sex, if it's at night, the
entire nighttime. You got a question, Charlie? Okay, fine. So let's finish
this point up.
הייתה למידה Hayeta lemuda ובתניא. vetanya. So now ובתניא רבי יהודה אומר
כל הלילה שלה. vetanya Rabbi Yehuda omer kol halaila shelah. Or it
says if it was at sunrise, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says sunrise
is off, the rest is okay, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
כל היום שלה, kol hayom shelah, the whole day is hers, which
basically means she's permitted. The way, I mean, the question is does
it mean the day is forbidden or the day is
permissible? רש"י Rashi says שלה shelah sounds like it's a good thing,
so רש"י Rashi says he means the
day, the day is okay, the night is forbidden. Either way, we
have a ברייתא braisa that contradicts it. ובתניא רבי יהודה אומר כל
הלילה שלה, vetanya Rabbi Yehuda omer kol halaila shelah, the night is
okay, the day is forbidden. לא קשיא, lo kashya, הא דהרגילה לראות
בתחילת יממא והא דהרגילה לראות בסוף לילא. ha dehargila lirot bitchilat yemama
veha dehargila lirot besof leila. When does she see? At sunrise. Does
she see after sunrise or right before sunrise? So if she generally
sees right before sunrise, then the night is off and the day
is okay. If she sees after sunrise, at or after sunrise, then
the day is. Often the night is okay. Now we learn a
lot of things from that. Number one we learn that the way
you define the units is by sunrise and sunset, not by עלות
alos and צאת, tzeis, which is what we normally do for הלכות
נדה. hilchos niddah. For whatever reason, it’s defined by sunrise and sunset.
So even if she saw ממש mamash a minute before sunrise, which
is after עלות, alos, it’s defined as night. Also it doesn’t matter,
even if she saw right at the cusp of the next period,
as soon as that period—as soon as the night is over she’s
totally permitted in the day. Or even if she saw right at
the beginning of the day, she’s permitted five minutes before as long
as it’s night. It’s very formalistic. It’s the entire unit she sees
in but not a second—she
doesn’t get someone that precise.
Right, exactly. Not a second before, not a second after. The other
interesting point is that you would imagine that it could be very
likely that a woman would see like, you know, spanning that, right
before to right after sunrise. So how do you determine that? So
the גמרא isn’t clear but the general consensus—some ראשונים Rishonim say okay
then both units are forbidden, but the general consensus is you go
by the beginning. Okay, so and therefore in that case if it
was from right before sunrise to right after, the nighttime would be
her וסת and not the day, although some say if she would
bleed five minutes into the day it would be the nighttime plus
five minutes. Yes.
The time of sunrise changes over the year unless you’re at the
equator.
Right, so you would have to assume that this is linked not
to the time on the clock but the time anyway, it's more
likely that a bodily thing would be linked more to the sun
than just to the time on the clock, I imagine. But yes.
So now the גמרא says, תני חדא, tany chada, we taught in
one ברייתא, braisa, רבי יהודה אוסר לפני וסתה ומתיר לאחר וסתה. Rabbi
Yehuda osra lifnei vesta umatir le-achar vesta. Rabbi Yehuda says before her—her
period it’s forbidden, after she’s allowed. ותניא אידך, ve-tanya idach, and we
taught in another ברייתא, braisa, אסורה לאחר וסתה ומתיר לפני וסתה, osura
le-achar vesta umatir lifnei vesta, after she’s forbidden, before she’s allowed. ולא
קשיא, ve-lo kashya, same answer. הא דרגיל למהוי בסוף לילא, ha d'ragil
l'mihvei b'sof layla, if she sees at the end of night, she’s
forbidden before but she’s permissible even a second after as soon as
sunrise hits. הא דרגיל למהוי בתחלת יממה, ha d'ragil l'mihvei b’tchilas yimama,
if she sees at the beginning of day, she’s—he’s forbidden after her
normal period of seeing sunrise. She’s forbidden for the rest of the
day, but she’s permitted up to a minute before. Right? So the
וסת here refers to not the whole day unit, it refers to
that time in the day she sees. So is she forbidden before
or after that time in the day? Really well, there’s no rule.
She’s forbidden during the unit in which that time occurs. Sometimes that
means before and after, most of the time. If it’s right at
the edge of a unit, then it could be either the entire
period before or it could be the entire period after.
Yes. Does it discuss the effect of the moon?
Because it seems like that’s more—we’ll talk about that in the next
משנה which talks about a relationship to, right, a relationship to the—to
the Hebrew month. So we’ll talk about that in the next משנה
which might be connected obviously to the moon. Okay, so we’ll get
to that discussion. Okay. אלא רבא, ella Rava, הלכה כרבי יהודה, halacha
ke-Rabbi Yehuda, we rule like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and that is
our הלכה halacha and that’s how we practice וסתות nowadays when it’s
a וסתות ימים vesta’os yamim not a וסתות הגוף. So the גמרא
says, ומי אמר רבא הכי, umi amar Rava hachi, did רבא Rava
really say that? והתניא, ve-hatanya, don’t we teach in a ברייתא, braisa,
והזהרתם את בני ישראל מטומאתם, ve-hizartem es benei Yisrael mi-tum’asam, you shall
warn the children of Israel from their impurities. So it means you
have to take extra care. מכאן אמר רבי ירמיה, mikan amar Rabbi
Yirmiyah, so here from here רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah says, some say
רבי יאשיה, Rabbi Yoshiyah, אזהרה לבני ישראל שיפרשו מנשותיהם סמוך לוסתן. azhara
livnei Yisrael she-yifreshu mi-neshisheihem samuch l’vistan. From here we learn a warning
that you have to—that the men have to separate from their wives
סמוך לוסתן samuch l’vistan before the period that they’re expected to become
to, you know, to get their—to get their period, to bleed, right?
Because that’s taking care, you know? So you have to separate a
little bit before because it might be—you don’t want to be having
sex when it happens.
Is this דאורייתא d’oraisa or דרבנן? de-rabbanan?
Well, yes, but well that’s a debate. There’s מחלוקת ראשונים machlokes Rishonim
whether this is a דאורייתא d’oraisa or an אסמכתא. asmuchta. וכמה, ve-chama,
how much do you have to separate? אמר רבא, amar Rava, עונה,
onah, an עונה onah which is a period which means either a
daytime unit or a nighttime period. So מאי לאו עונה אחריתי, mai
lav onah achmisi, now here the גמרא makes a very reasonable statement.
When we say if you see like at 12 o’clock you’re off
the whole day, that presumably is—that is the וסת itself, meaning with
a certain amount of a buffer zone and a certain amount of
maybe there's a certain variation. You’re, you know, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yoshi
says you can be very precise but we say the whole day.
Okay. But now we quote a פסוק pasuk that says you have
to separate סמוך לוסתן samuch l’vistan before the וסת. So that we
assume, doesn’t that mean that it—the period before the period? So if
a woman bleeds at noon, not only is the whole day אסור
assur but maybe the night before is also אסור? assur? Right, that’s
a reasonable read. מאי לאו עונה אחריתי, mai lav onah achmisi, does
not mean another עונה? onah? לא אותה עונה. lo osa onah. No,
it means that עונה. onah. It means that you’re not going like
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yoshi and saying just that one hour, you’re saying
the whole period before and after, you know, the whole day unit.
So therefore that’s the סמוך. samuch. The סמוך samuch is the time
around it. Now of course the funny thing is is that if
he sees at the beginning of the day, you’re not being separated
סמוך samuch prior, but you’re being separated סמוך samuch after. Okay, סמוך
samuch does not necessarily clear—סמוך samuch means in the environs. You have
to separate in the environs. So separating the whole day unit is
the—is you know, is a certain, you know, buffer zone although not
necessarily a prior buffer zone. It depends on— where that bleeding occurs.
But that's what we're saying. No, just that unit is enough. בתרתי
למה לי, Bitarti lama li, so why do I need both the
פסוק pasuk and the ruling like רב יהודה? Rav Yehuda, צריכה, you
need both. דאשמעינן הא, Di-ashmi'inan ha, if you had just said that
one about
about והזהרתם את בני ישראל, V'hizartem et bnei Yisrael, הוא אמינא hava
amina הני מילי hani mili לטהרה, letahara,
אבל לבעלה לא. aval l'ba'alah lo.
No, I'm sorry.
Yeah. If you had just said the one of רב יהודה, Rav
Yehuda, then because our משנה here is not clear that we're talking
about the husband, I would have just said, now it just says
אסורה, asura, both of them are אסורה. asura. Anyway, I would have
just said that it would have been primarily for טהרות taharas but
not for the husband.
קא משמע לן, Kamashma lan the פסוק pasuk of והזהרתם את בני
ישראל V'hizartem et bnei Yisrael which seems very much about sex, which
is, you know, the men have to be careful and so on,
which therefore is coming to tell me it's also about the issue
of sex, not just טהרות. taharas. אי מהיא, Iy me-hi, if it
was just the פסוק, pasuk, הוא אמינא hava amina סמוך וסתא עונה
אחריתין, samuch vesta onah achrisin, I would have thought that it meant
even more separation, even prior to the prior, even prior to the
unit. קא משמע לן אותו עונה, oso onah, only that unit itself.
So according to this, it is a little strange that you would
think that if a woman is going to see, expecting to see
at sunrise, you shouldn't be having sex ten minutes before that. Okay,
but in the end the גמרא very much formalizes and says no,
it's רב יהודה, it's the whole day unit or the whole night
unit, but regardless of when that occurs, and that is the separating
in the period in the time around the וסת, but not always
necessarily before. Now I should say by the way that there is
an opinion of the אור זרוע, Or Zarua, חומרא chumra of the
אור זרוע, Or Zarua, that some people even today are still מחמיר
machmir on, that basically is the rejected opinion here of the גמרא,
that says not only that עונה onah but the period before it
as well. Of course and then how do you read that in
the גמרא, you know, but nevertheless that is a חומרא chumra that,
and you understand where it's coming from, the same in the was
a serious הוא אמינא hava amina in the גמרא, but so that
is a חומרא chumra of the אור זרוע, Or Zarua, of course
that's not the general פשט, yes.
I mean, how can you how can you follow a rejected opinion?
Okay, so you have to see how they try to defend it.
But anyway, the last thing I will say is about Michael's question,
is this דאורייתא, de-Oraisa, is this דרבנן? de-Rabbanan? So here it quotes
a פסוק, pasuk, seems to treat it seriously, but there's other indications
that give some ראשונים, Rishonim, you know, some doubt.
So there is a question if this is for the גמרא in
שבועות. Shevuos. So there's anyway that there's sometimes it gets overridden, so
how do you override it if it's דאורייתא? de-Oraisa? So some say
it's דרבנן, de-Rabbanan, some say it's דאורייתא. de-Oraisa. I just want to
end by saying an interesting position of the ריטב"א Ritva that splits
the difference. And he says like the period right right around when
she's bleeding, you know, when she's expecting her period, maybe like an
hour before, whatever, you know, sort of a small circle around that,
that's דאורייתא. de-Oraisa. But according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, basically something
like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is דאורייתא, de-Oraisa, when you expand it
to the whole unit like רב יהודה, that already is a דרבנן.
de-Rabbanan. So there's interesting positions in the ראשונים Rishonim about how much
is this.